Guide to the Rae Armantrout Papers, circa 1970-2001 M.1211
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Rae Armantrout papers
circa 1970-2001
M.1211
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
10.5 Linear feet (21 manuscript boxes, 1 half box)
The collection documents Rae Armantrout's writing career from the 1970's through 2001.
Armantrout, Rae, 1947-
Access
The collection is open for research, except box 22, which is closed until 2021.
Acquisition Information
Accession numbers: MSS.2001-095, MSS.2001-140. This collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in April and May 2001.
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection contains correspondence, notebooks, typescripts, teaching materials, and photographs. Much of the correspondence, from the late 1970's to the present, consists of substantive letters and emails from other poets and writers, including Fanny Howe, Lyn Hejinian, Bob Perelman, and Ron Silliman. The notebooks in the collection record random thoughts from which Armantrout's poems often evolve, as well as multiple versions of both published and unpublished work. The collection also includes typescripts for Armantrout's books, including Precedence (1985), Necromance (1989), Made to Seem (1995), True (1996), as well as typescripts for other miscellaneous poems and essays. Teaching materials in the collection consist of Armantrout's lecture notes, syllabi, and course readers for classes on poetry and personal narrative taught at the University of California, San Diego from the mid-1980's to the present.
Biography
The poet and essayist Rae Armantrout was born in Vallejo, California on 13 April 1947 and grew up in San Diego. Graduating from the University of California, Berkeley in 1970, she later received a Master's degree in creative writing at San Francisco State University in 1975. Armantrout is the author of many books, including, among others, Extremities (1978), The Invention of Hunger (1979), Precedence (1985) Necroromance (1991), Made to Seem (1995), Writing the Plot about Sets (1998), True (a memoir, 1998), The Pretext (2001), Veil: New and Selected Poems (2001), Up to Speed (2004), and Next Life (2007). A founding member of the West Coast "Language Poetry" movement, Armantrout worked closely with a dynamic group of writers including Ron Silliman, Lyn Hejinian, Bob Perelman, Steve Benson, Barret Watten, Tom Mandel, and Carla Harryman. Although Language poetry can be seen as advocating a poetics of nonreferentiality, Armantrout's work, focusing as it often does on the local and the domestic, resists such definitions. Internationally known, Armantrout's work has been the subject of numerous essays (some of which are gathered in A Wild Salience: The Writings of Rae Armantrout, a collection dedicated to her work), and an entry in the Dictionary of Literary Biography (vol. 193). Currently, she teaches at the University of California, San Diego.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged in five series:
Series I: Correspondence
Series II: Notebooks
Series III: Writing
Series IV: Teaching Materials
Series V: Photographs
Other Finding Aids
Fanny Howe Papers, M0648, M0768, M0848
Marjorie Perloff Papers, M1504
Armantrout, Rae, 1947-; Davis, Lydia.; Hejinian, Lyn.; Howe, Fanny; Perelman, Bob; Silliman, Ronald, 1946-; American literature -- Poetry -- 20th Century; Women authors.
- Series I: CORRESPONDENCE
  Scope and Content
  This series contains incoming letters, postcards, and printed emails. Typescripts and other materials originally included with the correspondence have been retained in this series.
  - Abbott, Steve, 1979: letters (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Acker, Kathy, 1978-1980: letters, postcard (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Alcosser, Sandra, 1988: letter (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Alexander, Charles, 1990-2000: letter, emails (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Alferi, Pierre, 1991: letter (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Andrews, Bruce, 1977-1995: letters, postcards (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Armantrout, Hazel, 1989: birthday card (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ashbery, John, 1979-1992: letters (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Baracks, Barbara, 1976-1978: letters (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Bellamy, Dodie, 1995-1998: emails (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Benson, Steve, 1977-1992: letters, typescripts, postcards (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Bernheimer, Alan, 1985-1994: postcard, letter (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Bernstein, Charles, 1977-2000: postcards, letters, emails (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Berrigan, Sandy, 1988: letter (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Brito, Manuel, 1990-1994: letters, questionnaire (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Bromige, David, 1985-1997: letters, postcards, email (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Brooker, Gregory, 1994: letter, typescripts (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Brossard, Nicole, 1987: letter (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Brown, Colin, 1986: letters (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Brown, Lee Ann, 1994: letter (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Capgras, Genevieve, 1991: letter (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Chadwick, Cydney, 1989-1992: letters, postcard (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Chamberlain, Lori, 1988-1991: letters, postcard (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Codrescu, Andrei, 1993: letter (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Coleman, Wanda, 1990: letter (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Creeley, Robert, 1985-1999: postcards, email (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Cutler, Carolyn, 1991: letter (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Damon, Maria, 1995: email (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Darragh, Tina, 1987-1992: letters, postcards (Box 1, Folder 29)
  - Davidson, Michael, 1987-1991: letters (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Davies, Alan, 1979-1992: postcards, essay (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Davis, Lydia, 1983-1995: typescripts, letters, postcards (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Davis, Lydia, 1996-2000: letters, postcards, emails (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Destremau, Lionel, 1995: letter (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Doris, Stacy, 1994: letter (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Doughty, Julia, 1987: postcard (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - DuPlessis, Rachel Blau, 1984-1998: letters, postcards, emails (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Edwards, Ken, 1978: letters (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Equi, Elaine, 1992-2001: emails, postcards (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Eshleman, Clayton, 1970-1988: letters (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Evans, Steve and Jennifer Moxley, 1989-1992: letters, greeting card (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fraser, Kathleen, 1978: letter (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Freilicher, Melvyn, 1982-1992: postcards (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Gilonas, Harry, 1990: letters (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Gizzi, Michael, 1991: letters (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Gizzi, Peter, 1988-1997: letters, postcards, email (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Golding, Alan, 1992-1995: letters, email (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Grim, Jessica, 1989-1998: letters, postcards, email (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Hejinian, Lyn, 1977-1995: letters, signed broadside, postcards, typescripts, emails (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Hejinian, Lyn, 1996-2000: letters, emails (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Hocquard, Emmanuel, 1985-1986: letters, program (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Hoover, Paul, 1988-1994: letters (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Howe, Fanny, 1988-1995: letters, postcards, typescripts (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Howe, Fanny, 1996-2000: emails (Box 2, Folder 17-18)
  - Howe, Fanny, 1994-2000: emails. Closed until Jan. 1, 2021. (Box 22, Folder 1)
  - Howe, Susan, 1978-1996: letters, postcards, emails (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Jarolin, Edie, 1985-1991: letters, postcards (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Jorris, Pierre and Jerome Rothenberg, 1996: letter (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Killian, Kevin, 1989-1996: letters (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Killian, Kevin and Dodie Bellamy, 1996-2000: emails, letter (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Kinnell, Galway, 1990: letter (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Kitchell, Marilyn, 1986: letters (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Krantz, Chris, 1989: letters (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Lally, Michael, no date: note (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Lauterbach, Ann, 1991: letters (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Lazer, Hank, 1988-2000: letters, emails, typescripts (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Leddy, Michael, 1991-1995: letters, postcards, typescripts, essay on Armantrout (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Levertov, Denise, 1970-1978: postcards (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Littman, Brett, 1991-1993: letters, typescript, postcard (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Luoma, Bill, 1995: email (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Manson, Peter, 1994: letters (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Mayer, Bernadette, circa 1989: postcards, letters (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - McCaffery, Larry, 1991: letter (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - McGann, Jerome, 1989-1990: letters (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Merritt, Bruce, 1993: letter (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Messerli, Douglas, 1985-1997: letters, postcards, publishing agreement (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Moriarty, Laura, 1994-2000: letters, emails, wedding invitation (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Morrow, Brad, 1990-1995: letters (Box 3, Folder 23)
  - Mott, Glenn, 1991: letters (Box 3, Folder 24)
  - Moxley, Jennifer, 1991-1995: letters, typescripts (Box 3, Folder 25)
  - Mullen, Harryette, 1993: letter (Box 3, Folder 26)
  - Myles, Eileen, 1994: postcard (Box 3, Folder 27)
  - Neilson, Melanie, 1989-1995: letters, postcard (Box 3, Folder 28)
  - Nicholls, Peter, 1994-1995: letters, email (Box 3, Folder 29)
  - Nielsen, Aldon, 1992: letter (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Nowak, Mark, 1992: letter (Box 3, Folder 31)
  - Olson, Toby, 1985: letter (Box 3, Folder 32)
  - O'Sullivan, Maggie, 1994-1995: letters (Box 3, Folder 33)
  - Owen, Maureen, 1978: letter (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Perelman, Bob, 1978-1994: letters, postcards, typescripts, some with annotations by Armantrout (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Perelman, Bob, 1994-2001: emails; includes poems, some with annotations by Armantrout. (Box 4, Folder 2-3)
  - Perloff, Marjorie, 1994-2001: emails, letter, postcard (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Perry, Margeaux, 1989: letter (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Peterson, Jeffrey, 1995: essay on Armantrout (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Piombino, Nick, 1990: note (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Quartermain, Peter, 1995: email (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Raworth, Tom, 1990-1999: letters, postcards, email (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Reed, Pat, no date: greeting card (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Retallack, Joan, 1992: letter (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Robinson, Kit, 1978: letter, postcard (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Royet-Journoud, Claude, no date: letter (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Scalopino, Leslie, 1990: postcard (Box 4, Folder 14)
  - Schultz, Susan, 1990-1995: letter, email (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Sherry, James, 1992: letter, postcards (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Silliman, Ron, 1972-1994: postcards, letters, essay (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Silliman, Ron, 1994-2000: letters, emails, typescripts (Box 4, Folder 18-19)
  - Sloan, Margy, 1994-2000: letters, emails (Box 4, Folder 20)
  - Stein, Jean, 1990-1991: letters (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Swenson, Cole, 1992-1995: letter, greeting card (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Sze, Arthur, 1992: greeting card (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Waldrop, Rosemarie, 1983-1991: letters, postcard (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Ward, Diane, 1989-1998: postcards, note, email (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Watten, Barrett, 1985-1993: letters, greeting card (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Wheeler, Susan, 1997-2000: emails; includes typescript essay on Armantrout. (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - White, Shelly, 1990-1991: letters, greeting cards (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence: mostly emails; some letters, cards, typescripts. (Box 5, Folder 9-12)
  - Miscellaneous correspondence continued (Box 6, Folder 1-5)
- Series II: NOTEBOOKS
  The notebooks in this series contain drafts and notes for published and unpublished poems, as well as miscellaneous notes. Dated notebooks are arranged chronologically, followed by undated notebooks.
  - 1986 (Box 7, Items 1)
  - 1988-1989 (Box 7, Items 2)
  - Spring 1992 (Box 7, Items 3)
  - Fall 1992 (Box 7, Items 4)
  - 1992 (Box 7, Items 5)
  - 1992 (Box 7, Items 6)
  - 1992 (Box 7, Items 7)
  - 1992-1993 (Box 7, Items 8)
  - Summer 1993 (Box 7, Items 9)
  - Summer-Fall 1993 (Box 7, Items 10)
  - Fall 1993 (Box 8, Items 1)
  - 1993 (Box 8, Items 2)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 8, Items 3)
  - 1993-1994 (Box 8, Items 4)
  - Spring 1994 (Box 8, Items 5)
  - Summer 1994 (Box 8, Items 6)
  - Summer 1994 (Box 8, Items 7)
  - Summer 1994 (Box 8, Items 8)
  - Fall-Winter 1994 (Box 8, Items 9)
  - 1994 (Box 8, Items 10)
  - 1994 (Box 8, Items 11)
  - Winter 1995 (Box 9, Items 1)
  - Winter 1995 (Box 9, Items 2)
  - Summer 1995 (Box 9, Items 3)
  - Summer 1995 (Box 9, Items 4)
  - Fall 1995 (Box 9, Items 5)
  - Fall 1996 (Box 9, Items 6)
  - 1996 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - 1996-1997 (Box 9, Items 8)
  - Spring 1997 (Box 9, Items 9)
  - Spring 1997 (Box 9, Items 10)
  - Spring-Summer 1997 (Box 9, Items 11)
  - Fall 1997 (Box 9, Items 12)
  - Fall 1997 (Box 9, Items 13)
  - Fall 1997 (Box 9, Items 14)
  - Winter 1997-1998 (Box 10, Items 1)
  - Winter 1998 (Box 10, Items 2)
  - Winter 1998 (Box 10, Items 3)
  - Spring 1998 (Box 10, Items 4)
  - Spring 1998 (Box 10, Items 5)
  - Spring 1998 (Box 10, Items 6)
  - June 1998 (Box 10, Items 7)
  - Summer 1998 (Box 10, Items 8)
  - Summer 1998 (Box 10, Items 9)
  - Fall 1998 (Box 10, Items 10)
  - 1998-1999 (Box 10, Items 11)
  - May 1999 (Box 10, Items 12)
  - Fall 1999 (Box 10, Items 13)
  - 1999 (Box 11, Items 1)
  - 2000 (Box 11, Items 2)
  - Undated (Box 11, Items 3-13)
  - Undated continued (Box 12, Items 1-13)
- Series III: WRITING
  This series contains typescripts, proofs, periodicals, clippings, and other materials relating to Armantrout's publications and reading engagements. Loose typescripts by other writers have also been included in this series.
  - American Literature, 1993: letter (Box 13, Folder 1)
  - Best American Poetry, 1988: letter (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Clippings, circa 1986-1995: newspaper and magazine articles by or about Armantrout (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Davis, Lydia, circa 1994: End of the Story typescript (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Davis, Lydia, circa 1999: typescripts (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Delo, 1989: no. 8 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Equi, Elaine, no date: typescripts (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - The Germ, 2000: galley proofs (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Grand Piano Project, 2000-2001: emails (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Hejinian, Lyn, 1991: typescript (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - HOW(ever), 1983-1984: vol. 1, nos. 1, 3; vol. 2, no. 1 (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Howe, Fanny, no date: typescripts (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Interview, 1987: typescript interview of Armantrout by Lori Chamberlain (Box 14, Folder 1)
  - LANGUAGE, 1978-1979: nos. 2, 3, 5, 7 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Lazer, Alexander, no date: typescript of essay on Armantrout (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Made to Seem, circa 1995: typescript (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Necromance, 1989: typescript; includes letter from Sun and Moon Press. (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Necromance, 1989: proofs (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Neilson, Melanie, 1995: typescripts (Box 14, Folder 7)
  - Page Mothers, 1999: typescript essays by Armantrout and others (Box 14, Folder 8)
  - Partisan Review, 1981: letter (Box 14, Folder 9)
  - Perelman, Bob, no date: typescripts (Box 14, Folder 10)
  - Perelman, Bob, 1998: annotated proof for The Future of Memory (Box 14, Folder 11)
  - Poetry Flash, 1979-1991: nos. 74, 148, 223 (Box 14, Folder 12)
  - Precedence, circa 1985: typescript (Box 14, Folder 13)
  - Prosodia, 1994-1995: letters (Box 14, Folder 14)
  - Reviews, circa 1989-2000: clippings, typescripts (Box 15, Folder 1)
  - Silliman, Ron, no date: typescript (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Sun and Moon Press, 1992-1993: royalty statements, publishing agreement (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - True, circa 1996: typescripts (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - True, 1996: page proofs (Box 15, Folder 5)
  - Tuumba Press, no date: broadsides (Box 15, Folder 6)
  - Typescripts, no date: poems and essays, many with extensive annotations (Box 15, Folder 7-9)
  - Typescripts continued (Box 16, Folder 1-7)
  - Wesleyan University Press, 1999-2001: emails, publishing agreement for American Women Poets of the Twenty First Century (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - A Wild Salience, 1998-2000: correspondence (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - A Wild Salience, 2000: page proofs (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Zyzzyva, 1993: letter, publishing agreement (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Miscellaneous writing, no date: typescript essays by Armantrout and others; includes flyers for readings and conferences. (Box 18, Folder 1-5)
- Series IV: TEACHING MATERIALS
  This series contains teaching materials, such as course readers and handouts from courses taught by Armantrout at the University of California, San Diego.
  - Syllabi (Box 19, Folder 1)
  - Course handouts (Box 19, Folder 2)
  - Course notebooks (Box 19, Folder 3-7)
  - Course readers, 1985-1987 (Box 20, Folder 1)
  - Course readers, 1988 (Box 20, Folder 2)
  - Course readers, 1989 (Box 20, Folder 3)
  - Course readers, 1991-1992 (Box 20, Folder 4)
  - Course readers, 1992 (Box 20, Folder 5)
  - Course readers, 1993 (Box 21, Folder 1)
  - Course readers, 1994-1996 (Box 21, Folder 2)
  - Course readers, no date (Box 21, Folder 3-4)
  - Naropa course packet, 2000 (Box 21, Folder 5)
  - Miscellaneous teaching (Box 21, Folder 6)
- Series V: PHOTOGRAPHS
  This small series includes one black and white portrait of Armantrout from a 1982 reading, snapshots from a later reading with Ron Silliman, and other miscellaneous snapshots of Armantrout and others.
  - Photographs, circa 1982-1996 (Box 21, Folder 7)